But this is just a quick video demonstrating how while loops work.
The main gist of this lesson is to have a look at the basic syntax of while loops.
Using a while loop to control LED, using serial input or sensor monitoring.
I think the demonstration is just going to be sensor monitoring, which will be a button.
And the rest of this lesson handles things like infinite loops, breaking out of loops, and how to deal with other serial connections, etc.
The real too-long-didn't-read of how to use while loops is this basic syntax.
While some condition, do stuff.
And it will just go through those steps.
We can see here that if we have int i, it's assigned to i.
While i is less than or equal to i.
Serial dot println i.
It will print 1, 2, 3, so on until 5.
And every time it will go through, it will increment this.
So, that's the condition, go down.
Let's build that.
I'm going to use this circuit diagram right here.
For two reasons.
One, it's pretty simple.
And two, it kind of builds into the challenge
of our little
lesson.
So, all it is, is a button.
Really naively plugged in.
I have a one
giga ohm resistor.
Doesn't matter what it is, as long as it's high.
And I'm fitting that into pin 2.
And I have a LED
plugged into pin 13
with a 220 ohm resistor.
And you can see that both my ground and my power
are plumbed in.
So, starting with a serial begin,
I'm going to program my first while loop.
So, I'm going to say int i is assigned to 0.
Because number lines start from 0.
And I'm going to say while i is less than or equal to 5.
I am going to serial dot println i.
And then I need to increment my
i's up.
Now, when this runs,
fingers crossed it runs first go,
we should see the output there.
And we can.
0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5.
Now, let's just step through that code
to watch it actually work.
So, our code stops here.
The code block has started.
I step forward.
I initialize
the serial connection.
I create a variable called i.
And I assign it to 0.
And now I'm going to say while i,
which is currently 0,
is less than or equal to 5.
I'm going to do some stuff.
Serial dot println i.
This should print 0.
And it will appear in assign time.
It's a buffer issue now.
But serial is now 1
because this increments it by 1.
And actually it might
because it's in the web client.
It will go through.
Character by character.
And we can see it's repeated again.
Now, let's,
let's play around with that
circuit that we had before.
This one here.
With that button and that LED.
So, that button,
if I remember correctly,
was on pin 2.
So, let's add that.
Button pin is pin 2.
And I'm going to make one for my LED.
Which is on pin 13.
I need to set my modes.
Now, my pin mode for my LED pin is,
is that an input or an output?
Are we going to read from
or are we going to write to?
Well, we're going to read from it.
So, it is a output.
It's sending stuff to us.
And,
my pin mode for my button
in,
um,
is an input.
And now,
I'm going to make another while loop.
The whole idea of this is that
the button only flashes
if I'm pushing that button.
Sorry, the LED only flashes.
I'm going to push the button.
So, I'm going to do the other logic first.
Right?
I'm going to go digital write,
LED pin,
high,
delay,
500.
Digital write,
LED pin,
low,
delay,
500.
Now, what's this condition here?
I mean, that's a good question.
Um, I think,
we should think about it.
Um, we want the button to,
to be depressed.
But, I'm going to write it in here
and then I'll make it neater afterwards.
So, I'm going to go
digital read.
Uh, the button pin
is equal to high.
And, let's see if this works.
It does not.
Stop simulation.
Let's have a look at our code.
Oh, that's probably because I had the debugger still on.
Uh, stop,
start simulation.
Let's get rid of this code.
Oh.
So, we can see the LED flashes
while I've got the button held.
And, it stops when I've turned it off.
However,
just be aware,
because we have delays,
it will block in that,
that passage.
I'll show you what I mean.
If I press
the button once,
you see how it said on
and then turned off.
If we had, say,
a whole list of LEDs here,
they were all
pulsing on a delay,
then turning it on would make it go until that code block
is complete.